Shadows and Tall
Trees. The Pig Run kept close to the jumble of rocks that lay down by the
water on the other side, and Ralph was content to follow Jack along it. If you
could shut your ears to the slow suck down of the sea and boil of the return,
if you could forget how done and unvisited were the fern coverts on
either side, then there was a chance that you might put the beast out of mind
and dream for a while. The sun had swung over the vertical, and the afternoon
heat was closing in on the island. Ralph passed a message forward to Jack, and
when they next came to fruit, the whole party stopped and ate. Sitting, Ralph
was aware of the heat for the first time that day. He pulled distastefully at his
gray shirt, and wondered whether he might undertake the adventure of washing
it. Sitting under what seemed an unusual heat, even for this island, Ralph
planned his toilet. He would like to have a pair of scissors and cut this
hair. He flung the mass back, cut this filthy hair right back to half an inch.
He would like to have a bath, a proper wallow with soap. He passed his tongue
experimentally over his teeth and decided that a toothbrush would come in
handy, too. Then there were his nails.
Ralph turned his hand over and examined them. They were bitten down to the
quick, though he could not remember when he had restarted this habit, nor any
time when he indulged it. Be sucking my thumb next. He looked round fertively.
Apparently, no one had heard. The hunters sat stuffing themselves with
this easy meal, trying to convince themselves that they got sufficient kick
out of bananas and that other olive gray jelly-like fruit. With the memory of his
sometime clean self as a standard, Ralph looked them over. They were dirty, not
with the spectacular dirt of boys who have fallen into mud or been brought
down hard on a rainy day. Not one of them was an obvious subject for a
shower, and yet hair much too long tangled here and there, knotted around a
dead leaf for a twig. Faces cleaned fairly well by the process of eating and
sweating, but marked in the less accessible angles with a kind of shadow.
Clothes worn away, stiff like his own with sweat, put on not for decorum or
comfort, but out of custom, the skin of the body, scurfy with brine. He
discovered with a little fall of a heart that these were the conditions he took
as normal now, and that he did not mind.
He sighed and pushed away the stock from which he had stripped the fruit. Already
the hunters were stealing away to do their business in the woods or down by
the rocks. He turned and looked out to see. Here on the other side of the
island, the view was utterly different.
The filming enchantments of Mirage could not endure the cold ocean water, and the
horizon was hard, clipped blue. Ralph wandered down to the rocks. Down here,
almost on a level with the sea, you could follow with your eye the ceaseless
bulging passage of the deep sea waves.
They were miles wide, apparently not breakers or the banked ridges of shallow
water. They traveled the length of the island with an air of disregarding it
and being set on other business. They were less a progress than a momentous
rise and fall of the whole ocean. Now the sea would suck down, making cascades
and waterfalls of retreating water, would sink past the rocks and plaster
down the seaweed like shining hair.
Then, pausing, gather and rise with a roar, irresistibly swelling over point
and outcrop, climbing the little cliff, sending at last an arm of surf up a
gully to end a yard or so from him in fingers of spray. Wave after wave, Ralph
followed the rise and fall until something of the remoteness of the sea
numbed his brain. Then gradually the almost infinite size of this water
forced itself on his attention. This was the divider, the barrier. On the other
side of the island, swamped at midday with mirage, defended by the shield of
the quiet lagoon, one might dream of rescue. But here, faced by the brute
obtuseness of the ocean, the miles of division, one was clamped down, one was
helpless, one was condemned, one was Simon was speaking almost in his ear.
Ralph found that he had rock painfully gripped in both hands, found his body
arched, the muscles of his neck stiff, his mouth strained
open. "You'll get back to where you came from." Simon nodded as he spoke. He was
kneeling on one knee, looking down from a higher rock which he held with both
hands, his other leg stretched down to Ralph's level. Ralph was puzzled and
searched Simon's face for a clue. It's so big. I mean, Simon nodded. All the
same. You'll get back all right. I think so, anyway. Some of the strain had gone
from Ralph's body. He glanced at the sea and then smiled bitterly at Simon. Got a
ship in your pocket? Simon grinned and shook his head. How do you know then?
When Simon was still silent, Ralph said curtly, "You're baddy." Simon shook his
head violently till the coarse black hair flew backwards and forwards across
his face. No, I'm not. I just think you'll get back all right. For a moment,
nothing more was said, and then they suddenly smiled at each other. Roger
called from the coverts. Come and see.
The ground was turned over near the pig, and there were droppings that steamed.
Jack bent down to them as though he loved them. "Ralph, we need meat, even
if we are hunting the other thing. If you mean going the right way, we'll
hunt." They set off again. The hunters bunched a little by fear of the
mentioned beast, while Jack quested ahead. They went more slowly than Ralph
had bargained for, yet in a way he was glad to loiter, cradling his spear. Jack
came up against some emergency of his craft, and soon the procession stopped.
Ralph leaned against a tree, and at once the daydreams came swarming up. Jack was
in charge of the hunt, and there would be time to get to the mountain. Once,
following his father from Chaam to Devport, they had lived in a cottage on
the edge of the Moors. In a succession of houses that Ralph had known, this one
stood out with particular clarity, because after that house, he had been
sent away to school. Mommy had still been with them, and Daddy had come home every day.
Wild ponies came to the stone wall at the bottom of the garden and it had
snowed. Just behind the cottage there was a sort of shed and you could lie up
there watching the flakes swirl past.
You could see the damp spot where each flake died. Then you could mark the
first flake that lay down without melting and watch the whole ground turn
white. You could go indoors when you were cold and look out of the window
past the bright copper kettle and the plate with the little blue men. When you
went to bed, there was a bowl of cornflakes with sugar and cream and the
books. They stood on the shelf by the bed, leaning together with always two or
three laid flat on top because he had not bothered to put them back properly.
They were dogeared and scratched. There was the bright shining one about Topppsy
and Mopsy that he never read because it was about two girls. There was the one
about the magician which he read with a kind of tied down terror, skipping page
27 with the awful picture of the spider.
There was a book about people who had dug things up, Egyptian things. There
was the boy's book of trains, the boy's book of ships. Vividly they came before
him. He could have reached up and touched them. could feel the weight and
slow slide with which the mammoth book for boys would come out and slither
down. Everything was all right.
Everything was good humored and friendly. The bushes crashed ahead of
them. Boys flung themselves wildly from the pig track and scrabbled in the
creeper, screaming. Ralph saw Jack nudged aside and fall. Then there was a
creature bounding along the pig track toward him with tusks gleaming and an
intimidating grunt. Ralph found he was able to measure the distance coldly and
take aim. With the boar only 5 yards away, he flung the foolish wooden stick
that he carried. Saw it hit the great snout and hang there for a moment. The
boar's note changed to a squeal, and it swerved aside into the covert. The pig
run filled with shouting boys again.
Jack came running back and poked about in the undergrowth. Through here, but he
do us. Through here, I said. The bore was floundering away from them. They
found another pig run parallel to the first, and Jack raced away. Ralph was
full of fright and apprehension and pride. I hit him. The spear stuck in.
Now they came unexpectedly to an open space by the sea. Jack cast about on the
bare rock and looked anxious. He's gone.
I hit him, said Ralph again. And the spear stuck in a bit. He felt the need
of witnesses. Didn't you see me? Maurice nodded. I saw you right bang on his
snout. Wee. Ralph talked on excitedly. I hit him. All right. The spear stuck in.
I wounded him. He sunned himself in their new respect and felt that hunting
was good after all. I walloped him properly. That was the beast, I think.
Jack came back. That wasn't the beast.
That was a boar. I hit him. Why didn't you grab him? I tried. Ralph's voice ran
up. But a boar. Jack flushed suddenly.
You said he'd do us. What did you want to throw for? Why didn't you wait? He
held out his arm. Look. He turned his left forearm for them all to see. On the
outside was a rip. Not much, but bloody.
He did that with his tusks. I couldn't get my spear down in time. Attention
focused on Jack. That's a wound, said Simon. And you ought to suck it like
Barangaria. Jack sucked. I hit him, said Ralph indignantly. I hit him with my
spear. I wounded him. He tried for their attention. He was coming along the path.
I threw like this. Robert snarled at him. Ralph entered into the play and
everybody laughed. Presently they were all jabbing at Robert who made mock
rushes. Jack shouted, "Make a ring." The circle moved in and round. Robert
squealled in mock terror, then in real pain. "Ow! Stop it! You're hurting!" The
butt end of a spear fell on his back as he blundered among them. "Hold him!"
they got his arms and legs. Ralph, carried away by a sudden thick
excitement, grabbed Eric's spear and jabbed at Robert with it. "Kill him!
Kill him!" All at once, Robert was screaming and struggling with the
strength of frenzy. Jack had him by the hair and was brandishing his knife.
Behind him was Roger, fighting to get close. The chant rose ritually at the
last moment of a dance or a hunt. Kill the pig. Cut his throat. Kill the pig.
Bash him in. Ralph, too, was fighting to get near. To get a handful of that
brown, vulnerable flesh. The desire to squeeze and hurt was overmastering.
Jack's arm came down. The heaving circle cheered and made pigdy noises. Then they
lay quiet, panting, listening to Robert's fright and snibbles. He wiped
his face with a dirty arm and made an effort to retrieve his status. "Oh, my
bum," he rubbed his rump roofily. Jack rolled over. "That was a good game."
"Just a game," said Ralph uneasily. "I got jolly badly hurt at Rugger once."
"We ought to have a drum," said Maurice.
"Then we could do it properly," Ralph looked at him. "How properly?" "I don't
know. You want a fire, I think, and a drum, and you keep time to the drum."
"You want a pig," said Roger. Like a real hunt. "Or someone to pretend," said
Jack. You could get someone to dress up as a pig and then he could act, you
know, pretend to knock me over and all that. You want a real pig? said Robert,
still caressing his rump. Because you've got to kill him. Use a little one, said
Jack, and everybody laughed. Ralph sat up. Well, we sh find
what we're looking for at this rate. One by one they stood up, twitching rags
into place. Ralph looked at Jack. Now for the mountain. Shouldn't we go back to Piggy?
Said Maurice before dark. The twins nodded like one boy. Yes, that's right.
Let's go up there in the morning. Ralph looked out and saw the sea. "We've got
to start the fire again. You haven't got piggy specks," said Jack, "So you can't.
Then we'll find out if the mountain's clear." Maurice spoke, hesitating, not
wanting to seem a funk. "Supposing the beasts up there." Jack brandished his
spear. "Well kill it." The sun seemed a little cooler. He slashed with
the spear. "What are we waiting for?" "I suppose," said Ralph, "if we keep on by
the sea this way, we'll come out below the burnt bit, and then we can climb the
mountain." Once more, Jack led them along by the suck and heave of the
blinding sea. Once more Ralph dreamed, letting his skillful feet deal with the
difficulties of the path. Yet here his feet seemed less skillful than before.
For most of the way they were forced right down to the bare rock by the
water, and had to edge along between that and the dark luxurience of the
forest. There were little cliffs to be scaled, some to be used as paths,
lengthy traverses where one used hands as well as feet. Here and there they
could clamber over wave wet rock, leaping across clear pools that the tide
had left. They came to a gully that split the narrow foreshore like a
defense. This seemed to have no bottom, and they peered allstricken into the
gloomy crack where water gurgled. Then the wave came back. The gully boiled
before them, and spray dashed up to the very creeper, so that the boys were wet
and shrieking. They tried the forest, but it was thick and woven like a bird's
nest. In the end, they had to jump one by one, waiting till the water sank. And
even so, some of them got a second drenching. After that, the rock seemed
to be growing impassible, so they sat for a time, letting their rags dry and
watching the clipped outlines of the rollers that moved so slowly past the
island. They found fruit in a haunt of bright little birds that hovered like
insects. Then Ralph said they were going too slowly. He himself climbed a tree
and parted the canopy and saw the square head of the mountain seeming still a
great way off. Then they tried to hurry along the rocks and Robert cut his knee
quite badly and they had to recognize that this path must be taken slowly if
they were to be safe. So they proceeded after that as if they were climbing a
dangerous mountain until the rocks became an uncompromising cliff overhung
with impossible jungle and falling sheer into the sea. Ralph looked at the sun
critically. early evening after tea time. At any rate, I don't remember this
cliff, said Jack Crestfallen. So, this must be the bit of the coast I missed.
Ralph nodded. Let me think. By now, Ralph had no self-consciousness in
public thinking, but would treat the day's decisions as though he were
playing chess. The only trouble was that he would never be a very good chess
player. He thought of the Littles and Piggy. Vividly, he imagined Piggy by
himself, huddled in a shelter that was silent except for the sounds of
nightmare. We can't leave the Littles alone with Piggy. Not all night. The
other boys said nothing, but stood round watching him. If we went back, we should
take ours. Jack cleared his throat and spoke in a queer, tight voice. We
mustn't let anything happen to Piggy, must we? Ralph tapped his teeth with the
dirty point of Eric's spear. If we go across, he glanced around him. Someone's
got to go across the island and tell Piggy we'll be back after dark. Bill
spoke unbelieving. Through the forest by himself now. We can't spare more than
one. Simon pushed his way to Ralph's elbow. I'll go if you like. I don't
mind, honestly. Before Ralph had time to reply, he smiled quickly, turned, and
climbed into the forest. Ralph looked back at Jack, seeing him infuriatingly
for the first time. "Jack, that time you went the whole way to the castle rock."
Jack glowered. "Yes, you came along part of this shore below the mountain beyond
there." "Yes, and then I found a pig run. I went for miles. So, the pig run
must be somewhere in there." Ralph nodded. He pointed at the forest.
Everybody agreed sagely. "All right, then. We'll smash a way through till we
find the pig run." He took a step and halted. "Wait a minute, though. Where
does the pig run go to?" "The mountain," said Jack. "I told you," he sneered.
"Don't you want to go to the mountain?"
Ralph sighed, sensing the rising antagonism, understanding that this was
how Jack felt as soon as he ceased to lead. "I was thinking of the light.
Well be stumbling about. We were going to look for the beast. There won't
be enough light." "I don't mind going," said Jack hotly. "I'll go when we get
there, won't you? Would you rather go back to the shelters and tell Piggy?"
Now it was Ralph's turn to flesh, but he spoke desparingly out of the new
understanding that Piggy had given him.
Why do you hate me? The boy stirred uneasily, as though something indecent
had been said. The silence lengthened.
Ralph, still hot and hurt, turned away first. Come on. He led the way and set
himself as by right to hack at the tangles. Jack brought up the rear,
displaced and brooding. The pig track was a dark tunnel, for the sun was
sliding quickly toward the edge of the world, and in the forest shadows were
never far to seek. The track was broad and beaten, and they ran along at a
swift trot. Then the roof of leaves broke up and they halted, breathing
quickly, looking at the few stars that pricricked around the head of the
mountain. There you are. The boys peered at each other doubtfully. Ralph made a
decision. Well go straight across to the platform and climb tomorrow. They
murmured. Agreement, but Jack was standing by his shoulder. If you're
frightened, of course, Ralph turned on him. Who went first on the castle rock?
I went, too, and that was daylight. All right, who wants to climb the mountain
now? Silence was the only answer. Sam and Eric, what about you? We ought to go
and tell Piggy. Yes, tell Piggy that.
But Simon went. We ought to tell Piggy in case Robert, Bill, they were going
straight back to the platform now. Not of course that they were afraid, but
tired. Ralph turned back to Jack. You see, I'm going up the mountain. The
words came from Jack viciously as though they were a curse. He looked at Ralph,
his thin body tensed, his spear held as if he threatened him. I'm going up the
mountain to look for the beast now. Then the supreme sting, the casual, bitter
word. Coming. At that word, the other boys forgot their urge to be gone, and
turned back to sample this fresh rub of two spirits in the dark. The word was
too good, too bitter, too successfully daunting to be repeated. It took Ralph
at low water when his nerve was relaxed for the return to the shelter and the
still friendly waters of the lagoon. I don't mind. Astonished, he
heard his voice come out cool and casual, so that the bitterness of Jack's
taunt fell powerless. If you don't mind, of course. Oh, not at all. Jack took a
step. Well then, side by side, watched by silent boys, the two started up the
mountain. Ralph stopped. We're silly.
Why should only two go? If we find anything, two won't be enough. There
came the sound of boys scuttling away.
Astonishingly, a dark figure moved against the tide.
Roger. Yes, that's three, then. Once more they set out to climb the slope of
the mountain. The darkness seemed to flow around them like a tide. Jack, who
had said nothing, began to choke and cough, and a gust of wind set all three
spluttering. Ralph's eyes were blinded with tears. Ashes were on the edge of
the burnt patch. Their footsteps in the occasional breeze were stirring up small
devils of dust. Now that they stopped again, Ralph had time while he coughed
to remember how silly they were. If there was no beast, and almost certainly
there was no beast, in that case, well and good. But if there was something
waiting on top of the mountain, what was the use of three of them, handicapped by
the darkness and carrying only sticks?
We're being fools. Out of the darkness came the answer. Windy? Irritably, Ralph
shook himself. This was all Jack's fault. Of course I am, but we're still
being fools. If you don't want to go on, said the voice sarcastically. I'll go up
by myself. Ralph heard the mockery and hated Jack. The sting of ashes in his
eyes. Tiredness, fear enraged him. Go on, then. Well wait here. There was
silence. Why don't you go? Are you frightened? A stain in the darkness, a
stain that was Jack, detached itself and began to draw away. All right, so long.
The stain vanished. Another took its place. Ralph felt his knee against
something hard and rocked a charred trunk that was edgy to the touch. He
felt the sharp cinders that had been bark push against the back of his knee
and knew that Roger had sat down. He felt with his hands and lowered himself
beside Roger while the trunk rocked among invisible ashes. Roger,
unccommunicative by nature, said nothing. He offered no opinion on the
beast, nor told Ralph why he had chosen to come on this mad expedition. He
simply sat and rocked the trunk gently.
Ralph noticed a rapid and infuriating tapping noise, and realized that Roger
was banging his silly wooden stick against something. So they sat, the
rocking, tapping, impervious Roger and Ralph fuming round them. The close sky
was loaded with stars, save where the mountain punched up a hole of blackness.
There was a slithering noise high above them, the sound of someone taking giant
and dangerous strides on rock or ash.
Then Jack found them and was shivering and croaking in a voice they could just
recognize as his. I saw a thing on top.
They heard him blunder against the trunk, which rocked violently. He lay
silent for a moment, then muttered, "Keep a good look out. It may be
following." A shower of ash pattered around them. Jack sat up. I saw a thing
bulge on the mountain. You only imagined it, said Ralph shakily. Because nothing
would bulge, not any sort of creature.
Roger spoke. They jumped, for they had forgotten him. A frog. Jack giggled and
shuddered. Some frog. There was a noise, too. A kind of plop noise. Then the
thing bulged. Ralph surprised himself, not so much by the quality of his voice,
which was even, but by the bravado of its intention. We'll go and look. For
the first time since he had first known Jack, Ralph could feel him hesitate. Now
his voice spoke for him. Of course. He got off the trunk and led the way across
the clinking cinders up into the dark, and the others followed. Now that his
physical voice was silent, the inner voice of reason and other voices too
made themselves heard. Piggy was calling him a kid. Another voice told him not to
be a fool, and the darkness and desperate enterprise gave the night a kind of dentist's chair
unreality. As they came to the last slope, Jack and Roger drew near, changed
from the ink stains to distinguishable figures. By common consent, they stopped
and crouched together. Behind them on the horizon was a patch of lighter sky
where in a moment the moon would rise.
The wind roared once in the forest and pushed their rags against them. Ralph
stirred. Come on. They crept forward.
Roger lagging a little. Jack and Ralph turned the shoulder of the mountain
together. The glittering lengths of the lagoon lay below them, and beyond that a
long white smudge that was the reef.
Roger joined them. Jack whispered, "Let's creep forward on hands and knees.
Maybe it's asleep." Roger and Ralph moved on, this time leaving Jack in the
rear for all his brave words. They came to the flat top where the rock was hard
to hands and knees, a creature that bulged. Ralph put his hand in the cold,
soft ashes of the fire and smothered a cry. His hand and shoulder were
twitching from the unlooked for contact.
Green lights of nausea appeared for a moment and ate into the darkness. Roger
lay behind him and Jack's mouth was at his ear. Over there, where there used to
be a gap in the rock, sort of hump, see?
Ashes blew into Ralph's face from the dead fire. He could not see the gap or
anything else because the green lights were opening again and growing and the
top of the mountain was sliding sideways. Once more, from a distance, he
heard Jack's whisper. Scared? Not scared so much as paralyzed. Hung up there,
immovable on the top of a diminishing moving mountain. Jack slid away from
him, Roger bumped, fumbled with a hiss of breath and passed onwards. He heard
them whispering, "Can you see anything there?" in front of them, only three or
four yards away, was a rock-like hump where no rock should be. Ralph could
hear a tiny chattering noise coming from somewhere, perhaps from his own mouth.
He bound himself together with his will, fused his fear and loathing into a
hatred, and stood up. He took two lein steps forward. Behind them, the sliver
of moon had drawn clear of the horizon.
Before them, something like a great ape was sitting asleep with its head between
his knees. Then the wind roared in the forest. There was confusion in the
darkness, and the creature lifted its head, holding toward them the ruin of a
face. Ralph found himself taking giant strides among the ashes. heard other
creatures crying out and leaping and dared the impossible on the dark slope.
Presently the mountain was deserted, save for the three abandoned sticks and the thing that
bowed. Lord of the